<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flying | ericgideon.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://egid.github.io/category/flying/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://egid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-15T11:02:20-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://egid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Gideon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flight-seeing in Iceland]]></title>
    <link href="http://egid.github.io/flying/travel/flight-seeing-in-iceland/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T19:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://egid.github.io/flying/travel/flight-seeing-in-iceland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8088858114/" title="AlÞing (site of the world's first parliament), Þingvallir, Ísland by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img class="flex-content" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8183/8088858114_21298589de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="228" alt="AlÞing (site of the world's first parliament), Þingvallir, Ísland"></a></p>

<p>I previously talked about <a href="/flying/travel/flying-in-iceland">figuring out how to use an FAA certificate</a> and other steps towards flight-seeing as a pilot in Iceland. This is a more in-depth review of the planning involved, what I used, and where I went.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Planning</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8296171156/" title="Flying in Iceland! by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8500/8296171156_d7945a06ff.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Flying in Iceland!"></a>One of the major difficulties I had in researching my flights was getting charts and information about airspace and facilities around Iceland. I found this out too late to be of use for my trip, but airspace, airways, and other Icelandic chart data are now available online at <a href="http://skyvector.com/?ll=64.13042283188456,-21.94042969313066&amp;chart=301&amp;zoom=9">SkyVector</a>.  Their data compares accurately to the paper chart I borrowed, and can help with figuring out where to go and how to get there.</p>

<p>Airport (aerodrome) information can be found by browsing through the <a href="http://www.caa.is/FlugmalahandbokinAIP/AeronauticalInformationPublication/">Aeronautical Information Publication (AIP)</a>, the functional equivalent to a mashup of regulations similar to our FARs, some IFR enroute charts, and a couple of terminal approach diagrams and airport maps. Take your time and give it a read &mdash; everything is in English, and some parts are also in Icelandic. It isn&rsquo;t as bland as the FAR, so be thorough! Many airports have gravel runways and limited facilities, and you don&rsquo;t want to find out the hard way.</p>

<p>Weather information is available via the <a href="http://en.vedur.is/weather/aviation/">Icelandic Met Office</a>, where you can explore a rather nice selection of aviation weather products. Most of what you&rsquo;re familiar with in the states from the Aviation Weather Center is on hand, though often in a different format. Both of my flights were slightly iffy weather-wise &mdash; the fall &amp; winter leaves Iceland with lots of low scud much of the time, but when it clears, it&rsquo;s gorgeous. Give yourself some options and book a couple backup flights.</p>

<h3>Operational differences</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8295118463/" title="Flying in Iceland! by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8362/8295118463_13c692a37c.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Flying in Iceland!"></a>One of the weirdest mental changes I had to make was the flight plan system. Unlike the US, all flights must be on a flight plan &mdash; and (at least when operating at Reykjavik) you file with the control tower of the airport where you are based. Outside of towered airports I think you wind up filing and closing with the enroute ATC.</p>

<p>Also important to reiterate &mdash; most of the airports in Iceland are pretty bare bones even when compared to small fields in the US. Avgas is uncommon, and paved runways are a luxury. The gravel surfaces available are good, but they&rsquo;re still gravel. Don&rsquo;t expect to find a terminal or tiedown facilities everywhere, either.</p>

<h3>Language</h3>

<p>Everybody speaks English. Seriously, every single person I encountered in Iceland spoke incredibly fluent English. Pronouncing the names of places is intimidating, but it seemed like every Icelander had their own pronounciation, so I didn&rsquo;t run into any issues working with air traffic control. And of course, just like flying in the US, you can always just ask questions or state intentions in plain language and get your point across just fine.</p>

<h3>What it costs</h3>

<p>Probably the most important question anybody has about flying, but also probably the one with the most immediately outdated answers. <strong>Long story short &mdash; it costs more than the US, but much less than Europe.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.tskoli.is/flugskoli-islands/english">Flugskóli Íslands</a>, the flight school that I rented from, requires a checkout flight with one of their instructors before allowing you to rent solo. At the time that I was visiting, a Cessna 172S rented for <a href="http://www.xe.com/currencyconverter/convert/?Amount=24750&amp;From=ISK&amp;To=USD">24,750 ISK</a> an hour (wet), which converted to around $188, and the instructor rate was <a href="http://www.xe.com/currencyconverter/convert/?Amount=5900&amp;From=ISK&amp;To=USD">5,900 ISK</a> an hour, around $45. I flew with Kristófer, and he was professional, friendly, and more than happy to help us improve our trip, from picking a destination for our flight to suggesting restaurants in Reykjavik. The rentals have no minimum, which means you can book a plane for the length of time you think you&rsquo;ll need, and only pay for the block time &mdash; which is minutes elapsed from engine start to shutdown, for those used to Hobbs billing.</p>

<h3>Where to go</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8088859076/" title="Gulfoss (Golden Falls), Ísland by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8465/8088859076_36d89c1b3e.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Gulfoss (Golden Falls), Ísland"></a>After talking with our instructor and some of the other staff at Flugskóli Íslands, we settled on Stykkishólmur as our destination. It&rsquo;s a small city in the northwest of Iceland, and about .9 hours flying time away from Reykjavik &mdash; <a href="http://skyvector.com/?ll=64.61587193873675,-22.169311529060174&amp;chart=301&amp;zoom=5&amp;plan=A.BI.BIRK:G.64.1763235316484,-21.865539556414546:G.64.33538793457097,-21.830749517353265:G.64.9261025904075,-22.381896978271467:A.BI.BIST">here&rsquo;s an approximation of the route we flew</a>. We didn&rsquo;t have a ton of time to explore (I strongly recommend booking the airplane for the whole day) but it looked like a neat little fishing town.</p>

<p>Also recommended was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestmannaeyjar">Vestmannaeyjar</a>, an island community off the south coast. If you&rsquo;re less interested in getting out and exploring a destination, you could probably do an aerial <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Circle_(Iceland">Golden Circle Tour</a>). You wouldn&rsquo;t get up super close, but you would be able to see Þingvellir, Geysir (the original geyser), and the waterfall Gulfoss. Honestly, though, just getting into the air over Iceland is cool enough. The entire island is gorgeous, rain or shine, and it&rsquo;s an amazing experience. Enjoy, and if you&rsquo;ve got questions feel free to <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?screen_name=egid&amp;original_referer=http://ericgideon.com/flying/travel/flight-seeing-in-iceland/">ask me @egid on twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying in Iceland]]></title>
    <link href="http://egid.github.io/flying/travel/flying-in-iceland/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T17:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://egid.github.io/flying/travel/flying-in-iceland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8296170396/in/photostream/"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8351/8296170396_d4f6f7f4a7.jpg" class="right"></a>Shanna and I recently took a week-long trip to Iceland, where I was lucky enough to get some flying in. When we&rsquo;d  stopped over in Reykjavik for a couple days during a previous trip to Europe, I noticed how many light aircraft were in the air. The landscape is so weird and compelling that getting up in the air became a mandatory part of our return to Iceland.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, there&rsquo;s not a ton of information about flying in Iceland on an FAA certificate. I found a <a href="http://www.pprune.org/private-flying/116715-flying-iceland.html">2004 thread on the PPRuNe forum</a> that didn&rsquo;t offer much, and <a href="http://www.hang-out.co.uk/index.php/flying/iceland">another article</a> that had some useful info on where to fly, but prices &amp; recommendations from 1998. Eventually, I just scraped around the <a href="http://caa.is/english">English-language version of the ICAA website</a> (the Icelandic Civil Aviation Authority) and emailed them directly, asking what I needed to do to fly there. <!-- more --> I got a response within 24 hours:</p>

<blockquote><p>Foreign visitors in Iceland can use their valid and current ICAO pilot licence for three months for private VFR flights in Icelandic airspace in aeroplanes registered in Iceland. So as long you as licence is current and valid and you have sufficient privileges to fly the aeroplane in question. You can fly private VFR for three months in Icelandic airspace without having to validate your licence.</p></blockquote>

<p>Great news &ndash; no need for lengthy and costly process of validation. At this point, things got simpler, as the only task left was finding a place to rent an aircraft.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/8295117743/in/photostream"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8498/8295117743_549235b296.jpg" class="right"></a>I contacted <a href="http://www.tskoli.is/flugskoli-islands/english">Flugskóli Íslands</a> and <a href="http://www.icelandairclub.com">Iceland Airclub</a> to check prices and restrictions. There are other flight schools and rental FBOs, but the ones I saw didn&rsquo;t offer english websites, or were outside of Reykjavik, which excluded them right off the bat. Flugskóli Íslands has a fairly large fleet of Cessnas (C-152, C-172N, C-172S), allows solo rental with no minimum block time, and requires potential renters do a one-hour checkout with instructor. Iceland Airclub has a few PA-28s, but allows dual flights only – unless you pay dearly to become a member.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t really a difficult decision, once I had the information, and I scheduled a couple of flights with Flugskóli Íslands well in advance. They&rsquo;re the busiest flight school in Iceland, so this might not be a terrible idea. They&rsquo;re friendly and very responsive to emails, so don&rsquo;t hesitate to contact them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Onward &amp; Upward]]></title>
    <link href="http://egid.github.io/flying/onward-and-upward/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-26T22:59:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://egid.github.io/flying/onward-and-upward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/4468623772"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4009/4468623772_e32b324757_m.jpg" class="bodyimg right" title="" alt="" /></a> Over the last year, a lot has changed. I got married, flew our <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/sets/72157621661336277/">newly-restored &amp; upgraded Grumman</a>, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/sets/72157625344903588/">spent three weeks in Europe &amp; Iceland</a>, started looking into Masters programs, stopped instructing full time, and got a Real Job™. Oh, and http://aeronaut.ca now redirects to http://ericgideon.com, so update your shit. It&#8217;s been a fun year, I&#8217;ve enjoyed the changes so far, and I&#8217;m looking forward to what the future holds. The only downside to leaving instruction is that I spend a lot of time wishing I was flying, but &#8211; and this is key &#8211; <em>all of my flying I now enjoy</em>.</p>




<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/5370021667/"><img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5166/5370021667_9714564a9b_m.jpg" class="bodyimg left" title="" alt="" /></a> Anyway, this last fall was a lot of fun. The two of us went to the Reno Air Races, then visited Germany &amp; Austria, via Iceland. Flying Icelandair was an interesting look at how small airlines can serve smaller markets with narrow routes and the appropriate aircraft. Not to mention, their <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/5451625367/">branding</a> (and cabin crew) was fantastic.</p>




<p>As far as the future goes, I&#8217;m looking heavily into masters programs in the field of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_factors">Human Factors</a>, with the goal of taking that degree into the aviation industry. I&#8217;ve spent so much time working with technology &amp; usability, both in aviation and in web design, that I can&#8217;t see any other path but this. If you&#8217;ve got advice or thoughts on human factors &amp; aviation, I would welcome your input!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
