<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open-source | ericgideon.com]]></title>
  <link href="https://ericgideon.com/category/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ericgideon.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-12T13:47:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://ericgideon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Gideon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building and Flying with Stratux ADS-B In, part 2]]></title>
    <link href="https://ericgideon.com/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-ads-b-in-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-17T18:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://ericgideon.com/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-ads-b-in-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over a year ago I wrote about my initial experiences building and testing out the <a href="https://github.com/cyoung/stratux">open-source Stratux</a> ADS-B In receiver. I&rsquo;ve gotten more involved with the project since then, testing out new hardware and changing my existing build. I&rsquo;ve also had the chance to use some competing hardware!</p>

<h2>TL;DR: build yourself this $140 Stratux</h2>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th align="right"> Cost      </th>
<th> Description </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 37.20  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2utYnC6">Raspberry Pi 3</a> to run the whole show</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 14.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2tA1ALP">8GB SD card with Stratux installed</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 39.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2tzVoUf">Tuned antennas and radios</a> for receiving weather and two traffic channels</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 14.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2tkrXu9">GPS receiver</a> for integrated position data</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 14.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2utOaFz">ABS plastic case</a>, designed by /u/helno of Reddit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $ 12.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2t9LcCh">Anker 24W 12VDC charger</a> can run both an iPad and your Stratux</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">  $  6.99  </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/2talwoZ">Anker 10' USB cable</a> lets you position the Stratux anywhere in the cockpit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"><strong>$142.14</strong></td>
<td> <strong>total price</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<br/>


<p>If you&rsquo;re a pilot without existing access to ADS-B In weather and traffic, build this list. The same results <a href="http://ericgideon.com/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-homebuilt-ads-b-in/">cost $233 a year ago</a>, and the software has matured while the hardware has improved. For under $150, you can get dual-band ADS-B In traffic and weather with WAAS position data. It&rsquo;s fantastic.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>In use</h2>

<p>The one thing you might want to add is suction cups or velcro tape to position the unit. I fly a Grumman AA-1A, which (like the AA-5 Traveler/Cheetah and AG-5B Tiger) has an aluminum honeycomb fuselage structure. My best reception involved positioning the  with the antennas in a vertical orientation. This would not be as necessary in something like a Piper or Cessna.</p>

<p><img src="/images/stratux_2.jpg" alt="Current setup" /></p>

<p>As far as the reception performance goes, it ranges from &lsquo;decent&rsquo; to &lsquo;great&rsquo;, depending on the situation. I found that signal strength for traffic is often far better than that for weather. Still, in the Seattle area, I frequently see 4 or more ground stations in ForeFlight, which keeps weather up to date satisfactorily. South of Portland, reception can drop to a single tower. I haven&rsquo;t compared this to a Stratus 2S unit, but minimal ground stations exist out there in the first place.</p>

<p>GPS reception isn&rsquo;t perfect &ndash; it&rsquo;s not an external antenna, so accuracy is typically good at best &ndash; but it&rsquo;s totally functional. I use ForeFlight track recordings to debrief instrument training and currency flights, and it works great.</p>

<h2>Compared to OEM equipment</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve flown with pilots who have Stratus 2S units, and they seem pretty comparable. ForeFlight AHRS fed by a Stratus 2S is glitchy but usable; new Stratux builds support AHRS with the right hardware, but I haven&rsquo;t been able to compare.</p>

<p>Two months ago, we installed the Stratus ESGi transponder in our Grumman. The ESG is an ADS-B Out transponder, with a hard connection to a battery-less &ldquo;Stratus 2i&rdquo;. Because it&rsquo;s receiving 978 and 1090 signals via the belly-mounted transponder antenna, the signal strength is exceptional and outperforms the Stratux&hellip; but installed cost was around $4,000. Getting similar performance for $150 is a steal.</p>

<p>Some in the community use a splitter to connect a DME belly antenna to their dual-band Stratux, and they report similar impressive results. If you&rsquo;ve got the old hardware still dragging along, getting an A&amp;P to rig up a BNC to SMA adapter can be a powerful option.</p>

<p>No matter what you build, check out the <a href="https://github.com/cyoung/stratux">community on GitHub</a> and consider contributing! There&rsquo;s a fair number of contributors on the <a href="http://slack.stratux.me/">Slack chat</a> as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building (and flying with) Stratux homebuilt ADS-B In]]></title>
    <link href="https://ericgideon.com/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-homebuilt-ads-b-in/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-26T15:18:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://ericgideon.com/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-homebuilt-ads-b-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3><a href="/flying/open-source/building-and-flying-with-stratux-ads-b-in-part-2/">UPDATE: new writeup 17 July 2017, with a new $140 parts list</a></h3>

<p>I first heard about the <a href="http://stratux.me">Stratux project</a> a few months back, in a <a href="http://reddit.com/r/stratux">subreddit</a> that described how to build your own ADS-B In receiver for under $120. It uses software-defined radios to pick up ADS-B data, then processes it using <a href="http://github.com/cyoung/stratux">open-source software</a>. As a pilot who&rsquo;s dabbled with the idea of plunking down around $1000 on the Stratus 2S, this was a pretty attractive idea: less than $200 for traffic and weather on my iPad? Heck, I could build a receiver and order a new iPad for less than the list price of the Stratus.</p>

<p>I took the plunge, ordered the parts, and tried it out.</p>

<p>The verdict? It works brilliantly.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I started with the suggested parts to build a single-radio device, much like the original Stratus or the new 1S, and spent around $10 more on a slightly better external battery pack. Assembly is simple: plug the radios into the USB ports, and (if you&rsquo;ve got a case) screw the Raspberry Pi down. Here&rsquo;s my original build:</p>

<p><img src="/images/stratux_v1.jpg" alt="Original setup" /></p>

<ul>
<li>$69.99: <a href="http://amzn.to/1pPNaGh">Vilros Raspberry Pi 2 starter kit</a> &ndash; now sold with the Raspberry Pi 3. Comes with a case, SD card, and wall power.</li>
<li>$22.50: <a href="http://amzn.to/1Pxtz20">NooElec NESDR Mini 2</a> &ndash; this is the software-defined radio that receives ADS-B data. <strong>Note</strong>: don&rsquo;t buy this one, get the newer Nano 2.</li>
<li>$36.99: <a href="http://amzn.to/1Pxs18a">Anker Astro E5</a> power bank. I wouldn&rsquo;t recommend this purely because of how massive it is. Use ship power or a smaller battery.</li>
<li>After tax, this put me at $142.42, not including the blue tape &ndash; still pretty reasonable.</li>
</ul>


<p>This build got me the bare minimum: 978Mhz (UAT) weather, plus traffic if we were near enough to an ADS-B Out equipped aircraft to get the messages meant for them. After reading some more posts that added GPS (and the possibility of AHRS &ndash; basically making it a Stratus 2S), I ordered a Reyax RY835AI for $46.00 via eBay. This GPS isn&rsquo;t recommended anymore, as it&rsquo;s glitchy and require soldering, but it works fine.</p>

<p>That setup &ndash; GPS + 978Mhz &ndash; took us to Reno for the Air Races, and worked flawlessly the whole way. Between Seattle and Sacramento, where we picked up our car, we saw between one and three ADS-B towers the entire trip.</p>

<p><img src="/images/stratux_installed.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>After that first trip proved how useful it was, getting us weather and traffic far in advance and with very little workload, I&rsquo;ve gotten more involved in the Stratux community and continued building out my receiver. After a few others had success with using MakeXYZ to 3D-print cases, I ordered one and set it up.</p>

<p>More recently, I picked up two of the newer NooElec Nano2 SDRs to save space, then joined them to share a single antenna. Here&rsquo;s the current parts list:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th align="right"> Cost        </th>
<th> Description </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $38.70      </td>
<td> 3D printed case designed by /u/helno and printed by MakeXYZ. If I was to do this again, I&rsquo;d go for <a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:1182619">a newer, cheaper design</a> that he recently published.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $69.99      </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1pPNaGh">Vilros Raspberry Pi 2 starter kit</a>, as before</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $49.90      </td>
<td> 2&times; <a href="http://amzn.to/1pPPKvH">NooElec NESDR Nano 2</a>, slightly more expensive at $24.95 but around 1/3 the size of the original radio</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $46.00      </td>
<td> RY835AI GPS from eBay &ndash; if I was building new, I&rsquo;d use the <a href="http://amzn.to/1pPQ4KZ">Diymall VK-172</a> GPS for $25.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $ 9.99      </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1pPQ9hV">SMA female to Y type 2X L MCX y-splitter pigtail</a>, which allows me to join both radios to a single antenna at the cost of reduced reception</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $ 8.35      </td>
<td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1Pxu8ZJ">6' SMA extension cable</a>, currently around $12.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> $10.39      </td>
<td> <a href="https://www.digikey.com/product-detail/en/linx-technologies-inc/ANT-916-CW-HWR-SMA/ANT-916-CW-HWR-SMA-ND/1139580">Digikey ANT-916-CW-HWR-SMA-ND</a> antenna, based on some reddit users' recommendations</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"> <strong>$233.32</strong> </td>
<td> <strong>total</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><img src="/images/stratux_mounted2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also got a 10' USB extension cable, and a 2-port, 2.1A car charger that provides power for the Stratux and one iPad or smartphone. This means you can skip the battery pack, or get a much smaller one for backup purposes. The 10' cable allows me to mount it in the back of the baggage compartment, and the 6' SMA cable lets the antenna hang in the center of the cabin where it gets the best reception.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to blow past the original $120 promise, but the value is pretty impossible to beat. Add in the fact that the community is very active on both <a href="http://reddit.com/r/stratux">reddit</a> and <a href="http://github.com/cyoung/stratux">github</a>, and you&rsquo;ve got a pretty much future-proof Stratus replacement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
