<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Aviation | ericgideon.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://egid.github.io/category/aviation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://egid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-29T19:55:12-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://egid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Gideon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teach Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://egid.github.io/Aviation/Code/teach-everything/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-15T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://egid.github.io/Aviation/Code/teach-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s always fascinated me that most pilots first become professionals as flight instructors. Before starting jobs at airlines or charter companies, most pilots' careers begin by teaching brand-new private students the basics of aviation. Not everybody is good, and most don&rsquo;t do it for long even if they are, but it&rsquo;s somehow become The Way It Works in aviation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/2545890511/" title="2,000 ft/min, Bend, OR by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3156/2545890511_a3c89a6f17_b.jpg" alt="2,000 ft/min, Bend, OR"></a></p>

<p>I spent three years teaching at multiple levels, and one of the first things I realized is just how damn hard it is to be an educator. I&rsquo;m not comparing the relatively straightforward, one-to-one tutoring that is flight instruction with teaching a classroom full of highschoolers, or anything like that, but it&rsquo;s tough. If you want to know a subject thoroughly, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching">teach it</a> &mdash; so, basically the opposite of that bullshit &ldquo;those who can&rsquo;t, teach&rdquo; saying.</p>

<p>The main textbook of a CFI course is the <a href="http://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/handbooks_manuals/aviation/aviation_instructors_handbook/"><em>Aviation Instructor&rsquo;s Handbook</em></a>, which dives into some of the psychology of learning. One of the core concepts is that students should move from simple to complex &mdash; &ldquo;everything from intricate cognitive processes to simple motor skills depends on what the student already knows and how that knowledge can be applied in the present.&rdquo; It works well, and allows people to pick up big ideas gradually and sanely.</p>

<p>What I find hard to believe, now that I&rsquo;ve moved into a field other than teaching, is how poorly understood some of these concepts seem to be. There are plenty of websites &amp; smartphone apps that offer up incredible complexity, but do little more than fire up an intro tour. These are shockingly useless, <a href="http://www.subtraction.com/2011/02/01/unnecessary-explanations">as Khoi Vinh explains so well</a>; most users won&rsquo;t be able to memorize what you&rsquo;re telling them &mdash; and this is an important distinction: you&rsquo;re <em>telling</em>, not <strong>showing</strong>. Luke Wroblewski spoke a bit about this issue in his <a href="http://adactio.com/journal/6051/">talk at An Event Apart</a>, suggesting that instead developers use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_in_Time_Teaching">just-in-time teaching</a> as people interact, like what Facebook does every time they launch a new feature.</p>

<p>The <em>Aviation Instructor&rsquo;s Handbook</em> suggests a similar technique, one that served me well in briefings and on flights: the accurately-but-uninspiringly-named &ldquo;Telling-and-Doing Technique&rdquo;. Unlike traditional lectures, the sequence of teaching &amp; demonstration looks like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/238642854/" title="DO NOT TOUCH GLASS by thatguyeric, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/93/238642854_edbbebad1c_z.jpg?zz=1" alt="DO NOT TOUCH GLASS"></a></p>

<ol>
<li>Preparation</li>
<li>Instructor tells + instructor does</li>
<li>Student tells + instructor does</li>
<li>Student tells + student does</li>
<li>Student does + instructor evaluates</li>
</ol>


<p>The parallels to interaction work pretty well &mdash; the sequence could probably be adapted to skip the instructor tells &amp; does stage, which would otherwise be a demo, instead moving straight into an interactive, prompted first-run through a series of features. Add in some context- or timing-aware hooks so that your walkthrough can fire a second time, perhaps if somebody seems stuck or inactive.</p>

<p>Barring a better tutorial, just get people using your app. Even better, introduce features in <a href="http://www.lukew.com/ff/entry.asp?1648">small, digestable chunks</a>, so that they can learn as they go. Skip the tutorial and let them learn by doing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Past & Future of Turboprops]]></title>
    <link href="http://egid.github.io/Aviation/the-past-and-future-of-turboprops/"/>
    <updated>2006-08-04T14:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://egid.github.io/Aviation/the-past-and-future-of-turboprops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hedgehog/11383470/"><img src="http://static.flickr.com/10/11383470_23b2988a2e_m.jpg" alt="Tupolev Tu-114" /></a></p>

<p>One of the last <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tupolev_Tu-114">Tupolev Tu-114</a> airliners has been sent to the scrapyard, leaving one of the fastest propeller aircraft in history with a mere handful of survivors. Flight Global has some <a href="http://www.flightglobal.com/Articles/2006/08/03/Navigation/179/208269/Pictures+One+of+last+remaining+examples+of+world's+fastest+turboprop%2c+Tupolev+Tu-114%2c+broken+up+at.html">photos and a brief article</a> on the matter. It&rsquo;s unfortunate the aircraft couldn&rsquo;t be saved, as it truly is one of the great technological breakthroughs of aviation.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s most amazing about the -114 is its performance. Based on the famous Tu-95 Bear bomber, it was one of the larger airliners of its day and could seat up to 220 passengers. It could reach 475 knots (880 km/h) and cruised at 415 knots (770 km/h) on the combined 60,000 shaft horsepower of its four gigantic <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuznetsov_NK-12">Kuznetsov NK-12 turboprop engines</a>. Maximum range was over 6,000 km, despite fuel burn figures that were probably marginal at <em>best</em>. That an airliner like this could be built in the late 1950s at a time when jet aircraft were viewed as the next best thing is remarkable.</p>

<p>The reason I mention this is the new generation of airliners that is currently under development. Efficient aircraft result in lower costs, a huge incentive for airlines to upgrade. Over 600 sets of &ldquo;blended winglets&rdquo;:bw have been shipped for the Boeing 737, each saving over 100,000 gallons of fuel per year. If one aerodynamic change can save a significant amount of fuel, imagine what entirely new aircraft will do.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatguyeric/296802300"><img src="http://static.flickr.com/99/296802300_1b39781a17_m.jpg" alt="Boeing's Muppets include the Fozzie, a twin-propjet design" /></a></p>

<p>Even better, picture what a modern Tu-114 could do. Already extensive work has gone into <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propfan">propfan</a> technology, basically the combination of a turboprop&rsquo;s efficiency and turbofan&rsquo;s high-speed performance. Modern composite materials could make the airframe strong, light, and aerodynamic. Bombardier&rsquo;s Noise and Vibration Suppression system has made their Q series far more comfortable than past propeller-driven aircraft. Several of <a href="what-happened-to-the-exchange">Boeing&rsquo;s &lsquo;Muppets&rsquo; designs</a>, unveiled a few months ago, appear to incorporate this kind of technology. Turboprops have been experiencing something of a resurgence in sales lately &ndash; <a href="http://airwaysmag.com">Airways</a> had an article on Bombardier&rsquo;s recent Dash 8 sales boom &ndash; with turboprop orders matching regional jets for the first time &ndash; and ATR has a much larger order backlog than usual.</p>

<p>Rising fuel costs are making high-frequency turboprop service a profitable alternative to regional jets in the short-haul sector. How long will it be until the same is true of domestic flights? Will the 737&rsquo;s equivalent, 20 years from now, be running on propfans?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
